<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lido:lido xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml" xmlns:lido="http://www.lido-schema.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <lido:lidoRecID lido:type="global" lido:source="Museum voor Schone Kunsten Gent" lido:label="dataPID">http://mskgent.be/collection/work/data/1994-F-5</lido:lidoRecID>
  <lido:objectPublishedID lido:type="global" lido:source="Museum voor Schone Kunsten Gent" lido:label="workPID">http://mskgent.be/collection/work/id/1994-F-5</lido:objectPublishedID>
  <lido:descriptiveMetadata>
    <lido:objectClassificationWrap>
      <lido:objectWorkTypeWrap>
        <lido:objectWorkType>
          <lido:term lido:pref="preferred" xml:lang="nl">wandtapijten</lido:term>
        </lido:objectWorkType>
      </lido:objectWorkTypeWrap>
      <lido:classificationWrap>
        <lido:classification>
          <lido:conceptID lido:pref="alternate" lido:type="global" lido:source="AAT">http://vocab.getty.edu/aat/300205002</lido:conceptID>
          <lido:term lido:pref="alternate">tapisserieën</lido:term>
          <lido:term lido:pref="preferred">wandtapijt</lido:term>
        </lido:classification>
      </lido:classificationWrap>
    </lido:objectClassificationWrap>
    <lido:objectIdentificationWrap>
      <lido:titleWrap>
        <lido:titleSet>
          <lido:appellationValue xml:lang="nl">Verheerlijking van Minerva</lido:appellationValue>
        </lido:titleSet>
      </lido:titleWrap>
      <lido:objectDescriptionWrap>
        <lido:objectDescriptionSet>
          <lido:descriptiveNoteValue xml:lang="nl">In 1716 bestelt het Kasselrijhuis van Oudburg te Gent een reeks van vijf wandtapijten met de verheerlijking van de goden. Het kasselrijhuis is in die tijd een leenhof van het graafschap Vlaanderen, gelegen binnen de omwalling van het Gravensteen. Reeds een jaar later sieren de tapijten de wanden van de grote collegezaal. Het wapen van de Oudburg, een sabel met een gevoegde poort van zilver gehouden door een geleeuwde luipaard, zien we op elk tapijt bovenaan in het midden. Tijdens de Franse Revolutie wordt het College van de Oudburg afgeschaft en het Kasselrijhuis gesloopt. Na een aantal omzwervingen krijgt de reeks uiteindelijk in 1904 een plaats in de erezaal van het Museum voor Schone Kunsten. Met De verheerlijking van Minerva wordt opnieuw het belang van de  beschaving beklemtoond. Minerva is, evenals Apollo, de antipode van Mars. Geboren uit het hoofd van Jupiter is zij de godin van de wijsheid, van de kennis en van de vrede. Als strijdbare godin kan zij vrede doen heersen en beschermt zij de beschaving, hier voorgesteld door verschillende allegorische figuren. De vrouw naast haar met de hoorn des overvloeds onder haar arm symboliseert de Voorspoed.  Verder zien we de Bouwkunst, de Beeldhouwkunst, de Schilderkunst, de Wetenschappen, de Poëzie en de Muziek. Allen komen Minerva eer betuigen. Op de voorgrond vernietigen twee putti oorlogstuig, terwijl de Faam de overwinning van Minerva met bazuingeschal verkondigt: de rede zegeviert over het zinneloze geweld. In de achtergrond zien we een ploegende boer en een haven. Zij staan voor de Landbouw en de Handel.</lido:descriptiveNoteValue>
        </lido:objectDescriptionSet>
        <lido:objectDescriptionSet>
          <lido:descriptiveNoteValue xml:lang="en">In 1716, the Viscounty of the Oudburg in Ghent commissioned a series of tapestries devoted to the Exaltation of the Gods. The Viscounty was a fief of the County of Flanders, located within the walls of the Counts’ Castle. Barely a year later, the tapestries were hung in the Castellany. The Oudburg arms appears in the middle of each tapestry. Oudburg College was closed down during the period of French revolutionary occupation and the Viscounty building was demolished. The series ended up in the Museum of Fine Art in 1904, having had several homes in the interim. The Exaltation of Minerva focuses again on the importance of civilisation. Minerva, like Apollo, is presented as the opposite of Mars. She sprang from the head of Jupiter, making her the Goddess of Wisdom, Knowledge and Peace. Minerva is a warlike goddess with the strength to impose peace and to protect civilisation, which are represented here by a variety of allegorical figures. The woman at her side, with the Horn of Plenty under her arm, is a symbol of Prosperity. Other figures include Architecture, Sculpture, Painting, Science, Poetry and Music, all of whom have come to pay homage to Minerva. Two cherubs destroy instruments of war in the foreground, while Fame trumpets forth Minerva’s victory – the conquest of mindless violence by reason. The farmer ploughing his field and the harbour in the background represent Agriculture and Trade.</lido:descriptiveNoteValue>
        </lido:objectDescriptionSet>
      </lido:objectDescriptionWrap>
      <lido:objectMeasurementsWrap>
        <lido:objectMeasurementsSet>
          <lido:objectMeasurements>
            <lido:measurementsSet>
              <lido:measurementType>hoogte</lido:measurementType>
              <lido:measurementUnit>cm</lido:measurementUnit>
              <lido:measurementValue>408</lido:measurementValue>
            </lido:measurementsSet>
          </lido:objectMeasurements>
        </lido:objectMeasurementsSet>
        <lido:objectMeasurementsSet>
          <lido:objectMeasurements>
            <lido:measurementsSet>
              <lido:measurementType>breedte</lido:measurementType>
              <lido:measurementUnit>cm</lido:measurementUnit>
              <lido:measurementValue>555</lido:measurementValue>
            </lido:measurementsSet>
          </lido:objectMeasurements>
        </lido:objectMeasurementsSet>
      </lido:objectMeasurementsWrap>
    </lido:objectIdentificationWrap>
    <lido:eventWrap>
      <lido:eventSet>
        <lido:event>
          <lido:eventType>
            <lido:term>Production</lido:term>
          </lido:eventType>
          <lido:eventActor>
            <lido:actorInRole>
              <lido:actor>
                <lido:actorID lido:type="local" lido:source="Adlib"/>
                <lido:nameActorSet>
                  <lido:appellationValue lido:pref="alternate"/>
                </lido:nameActorSet>
              </lido:actor>
            </lido:actorInRole>
          </lido:eventActor>
          <lido:eventDate>
            <lido:displayDate>circa 1717</lido:displayDate>
            <lido:date>
              <lido:earliestDate lido:type="Brussel">1717</lido:earliestDate>
            </lido:date>
          </lido:eventDate>
          <lido:periodName>
            <lido:term xml:lang="nl">18de eeuw</lido:term>
          </lido:periodName>
          <lido:eventPlace>
            <lido:place>
              <lido:namePlaceSet>
                <lido:appellationValue lido:pref="preferred" xml:lang="nl"/>
              </lido:namePlaceSet>
            </lido:place>
          </lido:eventPlace>
          <lido:eventMaterialsTech>
            <lido:materialsTech>
              <lido:termMaterialsTech lido:type="physicalDescription"/>
            </lido:materialsTech>
          </lido:eventMaterialsTech>
        </lido:event>
      </lido:eventSet>
    </lido:eventWrap>
    <lido:objectRelationWrap>
      <lido:subjectWrap>
        <lido:subjectSet>
          <lido:subject>
            <lido:subjectConcept>
              <lido:term xml:lang="nl">mythologie</lido:term>
            </lido:subjectConcept>
          </lido:subject>
        </lido:subjectSet>
      </lido:subjectWrap>
    </lido:objectRelationWrap>
  </lido:descriptiveMetadata>
  <lido:administrativeMetadata>
    <lido:recordWrap>
      <lido:recordID lido:type="local">1994-F-5</lido:recordID>
      <lido:recordID lido:type="Adlib">310005635</lido:recordID>
      <lido:recordType>
        <lido:conceptID lido:type="local" lido:source="AAT">http://vocab.getty.edu/aat/300133025</lido:conceptID>
        <lido:term>Item</lido:term>
      </lido:recordType>
      <lido:recordSource>
        <lido:legalBodyName>
          <lido:appellationValue>Museum voor Schone Kunsten Gent</lido:appellationValue>
        </lido:legalBodyName>
        <lido:legalBodyWeblink>http://mskgent.be</lido:legalBodyWeblink>
      </lido:recordSource>
    </lido:recordWrap>
  </lido:administrativeMetadata>
</lido:lido>
